Leah: So, what exactly is deployment?
Deployment is the process of making new and
existing software products that have been
completed, available and accessible to users.
Deployment activities include ‘software
releases’, ‘installation’, ‘testing’,
and ‘performance monitoring’.
Deployment planning is critical for software
deployment to be successful, it can be
manual, but can also be automated, which
makes it more efficient and effective.
For ‘deployment planning’ the project leader would
outline the scope, approach, and delivery method.
Chris: Let’s have a look at what
‘Deployment planning’ would include:
Summary of the deployment goals, which would
include the target date, scope of the work,
version release goal, and the schedule.
Deployment schedule, created to break down
manageable tasks which are assigned to specific
team members with planned duration and dates.
List of the requirements or resources
needed, for a successful deployment such as
hardware, software, skillsets, staff time etc.
Leah: Document and mitigate risks,
potential risks are listed with possible
impact on the deployment and the steps
to mitigate each risk are documented.
This would include a rollback strategy.
Communication, a plan to outline how team
members will communicate so everyone knows
their role and can keep track of tasks.
The plan would outline each step of the
deployment process in detail and each
of these processes would be tracked.
A software tool such as a Release management tool
could be used to automate the deployment plan.
Chris: So, why is deployment planning important?
Because of the deployment schedule and that the
resources are determined, this helps developers
to ‘save time’ as all the resources will be in
place before the software product release happens.
Leah: Following the processes from software
releases to performance monitoring sequentially,
will ensure timely feedback, meaning that
developers will be able to evaluate the
‘efficiency’ of the product properly.
This in turn will ‘increase productivity’ and
add value to the product for the end users.
Chris: As developers can measure the efficiency
of the product and get feedback from the
user, this will help to keep in mind, what
a ‘real end user’ wants from the product.
For example, a feature of the product
that a user would consider important,
could be included in the next release.
This would retain existing users and reach out to
new ones therefore increasing the customer base.
Leah: If the deployment is planned properly,
this will help the team to be clear on at
what stage of the project they are at, their
current tasks, and what their priorities are.
It also helps when a new developer is brought into
the team, as processes are documented properly.
Chris: It is important to document the ‘risks’ of
software deployment, as they could be ‘mitigated’
with testing before the product is deployed.
Risks could include a product that
crashes, has bugs, has performance issues,
and does not add value to the end user.
The product can be monitored for responsiveness
and performance in the right test environment.
One important risk that will need to be
considered is if the deployment needs
to be rolled back to a previous version.
A good deployment plan would include a
rollback strategy which we will look at
in more detail later in this section.